I am the head of Human-Computer Interaction research at Lilt, using Data Science, Machine Learning, and Interactive Machine Translation to boost translator productivity. During my Ph.D at Stanford, I built HabitLab, an app for data-driven behavior change with 12,000+ daily active users. I have published first-author papers in venues including CHI, CSCW, and Learning@Scale, and have reviewed, served on committees, and given invited talks at WMT, EACL, AMTA, CHI, UIST, CSCW, and IMWUT. I have been awarded the NSF and NDSEG Fellowships, and a Stanford Human-Centered AI Grant. I wrote and maintain UNetbootin, an open-source project with 40 million downloads.

#### **Education**

Ph.D, Computer ScienceStanford UniversityGPA: 4.0/4.02019B.S. and M.Eng, Computer ScienceMassachusetts Institute of TechnologyGPA: 5.0/5.02013

## **Work Experience**

Principal Research Scientist Lilt San Francisco
Senior Research Scientist Lilt San Francisco

Feb 2021 - present Aug 2019 - Feb 2021

I am the head of HCI research and manage a team of researchers at Lilt, an interactive machine translation startup. Improved interactive MT system speed by shifting computation client-side via TensorflowJS and heuristics. Built named entity transliteration system based on Transformer architecture using tensor2tensor and Tensorflow. Developed metrics and logging to determine how translators spend their time and predict translator performance. Ran A/B tests to evaluate website translation ROI, and developed system that recommends pages to translate.

Research Intern Microsoft Research Redmond

Summer 2015

Designed and built an educational social feed app usable by pre-literate children. Published at CSCW 2017.

Research Intern Microsoft Research Beijing

Summer 2014

Built QuizCram, a quiz-driven MOOC lecture viewer that improves learning outcomes. Presented at CHI 2015.

**Software Engineering Intern** Google Mountain View

Summer 2013

Developed a machine learning system for detecting taps on the phone bezel, for use in Android input methods.

**Software Engineering Intern** Google Mountain View

Summer 2012

Developed an NLP system to automatically generate glossaries from book text. Patent granted US9483460B2.

Software Engineering Intern Google Mountain View

Summer 2011

Developed a machine learning system to predict the quality of user reviews, now deployed on Google Play.

Software Development Engineer Intern Microsoft Redmond

Summer 2010

Built the IntelliSense code completion system for a scientific computing language, and contributed to its compiler.

### **Skills and Technologies**

Programming Languages: Python, JavaScript, C, C++, Java, TypeScript, R, C#, HTML, CSS, SQL, Bash Machine Learning + Deep Learning: Tensorflow, PyTorch, scikit-learn, TensorflowJS, xgboost, MLFlow Natural Language Processing + Machine Translation: Transformer, tensor2tensor, fairseq, SpaCy, LASER, BERT Data Science + Visualization: NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, Jupyter, RStudio, Plotly, D3.js, MySQL, Hadoop, MapReduce Web + Mobile Development: HTML, CSS, React, AngularJS, NodeJS, Express, Flask, Polymer, Docker, Android Languages: Fluent: English, Chinese (Mandarin), Hungarian. Intermediate: Japanese, Vietnamese, Spanish.

### **Publications in Journals and Conference Proceedings**

**Geza Kovacs**, Zhengxuan Wu, Michael Bernstein. "Not Now, Ask Later: Users Weaken Their Behavior Change Regimen Over Time, But Expect To Re-Strengthen It Imminently." *ACM annual conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) 2021.* 

Samuel Läubli, Patrick Simianer, Joern Wuebker, **Geza Kovacs**, Rico Sennrich, Spence Green. "The Impact of Text Presentation on Translator Performance." *Target: International Journal of Translation Studies, 2021 (to appear).* 

**Geza Kovacs**, Drew Mylander Gregory, Zilin Ma, Zhengxuan Wu, Golrokh Emami, Jacob Ray, Michael Bernstein. "Conservation of Procrastination: Do Productivity Interventions Save Time Or Just Redistribute It?" *ACM annual conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) 2019.* 

**Geza Kovacs**, Zhengxuan Wu, Michael Bernstein. "Rotating Online Behavior Change Interventions Increases Effectiveness But Also Increases Attrition." *ACM annual conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW) 2018*.

Rajan Vaish, Neil Gaikwad, **Geza Kovacs**, Andreas Veit, Ranjay Krishna, Imanol Arrieta Ibarra, Camelia Simoiu, Michael Wilber, Serge Belongie, Sharad Goel, James Davis, Michael Bernstein. "Crowd Research: Open and Scalable University Laboratories." *ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST) 2017.* 

Kiley Sobel, **Geza Kovacs**, Galen McQuillen, Andrew Cross, Nirupama Chandrasekaran, Nathalie Riche, Ed Cutrell, Meredith Morris. "EduFeed: A Social Feed to Engage Preliterate Children in Educational Activities." *ACM annual conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW) 2017.* 

**Geza Kovacs**. "Effects of In-Video Quizzes on MOOC Lecture Viewing." *ACM annual conference on Learning at Scale (L@S) 2016*.

**Geza Kovacs** and Robert C. Miller. "Smart Subtitles for Vocabulary Learning." *ACM annual conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) 2014.* 

# **Publications in Adjunct Conference Proceedings**

Stanford Crowd Research, **Geza Kovacs**, Rajan Vaish, Michael Bernstein. "Daemo: A Self-Governed Crowdsourcing Marketplace". *ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST) 2015, Poster*.

**Geza Kovacs**. "FeedLearn: Using Facebook Feeds for Microlearning." *ACM annual conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) 2015, Extended Abstracts*.

**Geza Kovacs**. "QuizCram: A Question-Driven Video Studying Interface." *ACM annual conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) 2015, Extended Abstracts*.

Joseph Jay Williams, **Geza Kovacs**, Caren Walker, Samuel G Maldonado, Tania Lombrozo. "Learning Online via Prompts to Explain." *ACM annual conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) 2014, Extended Abstracts.* 

**Geza Kovacs** and Robert C. Miller. "Foreign Manga Reader: Learn Grammar and Pronunciation while Reading Comics." *ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST) 2013, Demo.* 

**Geza Kovacs**. "Smart Subtitles for Language Learning." *ACM annual conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) 2013, Extended Abstracts*.

**Geza Kovacs**. "ScreenMatch: providing context to software translators by displaying screenshots." *ACM annual conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) 2012, Extended Abstracts*.

#### **Patents**

Tania Bedrax-Weiss, **Geza Kovacs**, Ulas Kirazci. "Automated formation of specialized dictionaries." US9483460B2. Filed 10/2013, Published 11/2016, Expires 01/2034.

Meredith Morris, Nathalie Henry Riche, Edward B. Cutrell, Andrew C. Cross, Natasa Milic, Nirupama Chandrasekaran, Galen McQuillen, Kiley Sobel, **Geza Kovacs**. "Presenting educational activities via an extended social media feed." US20180068578A1. Filed 09/2016, Published 03/2018.

## **Open-source Projects**

**UNetbootin (LiveUSB Creator)** 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNetbootin

40 million downloads. UNetbootin creates bootable USB flash drives for various (50+) Linux distributions.

**Ubuntu Installer for Windows (Wubi)** 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wubi\_(software)

Now part of Ubuntu. Built the first versions of Wubi, which allows Ubuntu to be installed from Windows.

HabitLab (In-the-wild Behavior Change Research Platform)

https://habitlab.stanford.edu

12,000+ daily active users. I built HabitLab over my Ph.D, and it is still used for research at Stanford Medical School.

# **Academic Conference Reviewing and Committees**

Organizing Committee, WMT 2022 Shared Task on Word-Level Auto-Completion	2021
Program Committee, EACL 2021 Bridging HCI and NLP Workshop	2021
Reviewer, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) 2015, 2018, 2019,	2021, 2022
Reviewer, ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSC)	W) 2021
Reviewer, ACM Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT)	2019
Reviewer, ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST)	2017, 2018

# **Invited Keynote Talks**

**Geza Kovacs**. "Predictive Translation Memory in the Wild: A Study of Interactive Machine Translation Use on Lilt." Association for Machine Translation in the Americas (AMTA) Workshop on the Impact of Machine Translation 2020.

# **Researchers Managed**

Sai Gouravajhala, Senior Research Scientist at Lilt.	August 2020 – present
Hannah Yan, Senior Data Scientist at Lilt.	September 2020 – present
Jordan Huffaker, Research Intern at Lilt. Now a Ph.D student at University of M	ichigan. Summer 2021
Jessy Lin, Research Engineer at Lilt. Now a Ph.D student at UC Berkeley.	August 2019 – August 2020
Ming-Chang Chiu, Data Science Intern at Lilt. Now a Ph.D student at USC.	Summer 2020
Zhengxuan Wu, MS student researcher at Stanford.	Fall 2018 – Spring 2019
Zilin Ma, undergraduate researcher at Stanford. Now a Ph.D student at Harvard	d. Summer 2018

# **Teaching Experience**

Understanding Users (CS 377U) – Teaching Assistant, at Stanford	Spring 2019
Human Computer Interaction Research (CS 376) - Teaching Assistant, at Stanford	Fall 2018
Natural Language Processing (6.863) - Teaching Assistant, at MIT	Fall 2012

## **Press Coverage**

#### **HabitLab**

<b>WIRED</b> - The HabitLab Browser Extension Curbs Your Time Wasted on the Web. https://www.wired.com/story/habitlab-browser-extension/	January 2019
Lifehacker - Prevent Procrastination With This Chrome Extension.	February 2019

https://lifehacker.com/prevent-procrastination-with-this-chrome-extension-1832723418

**The New York Times** - Finding It Hard to Focus? Maybe It's Not Your Fault.

August 2018 https://www.nytimes.com/2018/08/14/style/how-can-i-focus-better.html

**Lifehacker** - Be More Mindful of the Time You Waste Online With HabitLab. August 2018 https://lifehacker.com/be-more-mindful-of-the-time-you-waste-online-with-habit-1828118354

#### Crowd Research / Daemo

**Stanford University News** - A Stanford-led platform for crowdsourced research gives experience to global participants https://news.stanford.edu/2017/10/23/crowdsourced-research-gives-experience-global-participants/

**WIRED** - Amazon's Turker Crowd Has Had Enough.

https://www.wired.com/story/amazons-turker-crowd-has-had-enough/

## **UNetbootin**

**Forbes** - How To Try Linux Without Making Any Changes To Your PC. September 2018 https://www.forbes.com/sites/jasonevangelho/2018/09/18/how-to-safely-try-linux-on-your-mac-or-windows-pc/

## Wubi

**Ars Technica** - Wubi arrives: a look at Ubuntu 8.04 alpha 5. February 2008 https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2008/02/wubi-arrives-a-look-at-ubuntu-8-04-alpha-5/